Finding Aid for Dept. of Physical Education for Women (University of Michigan) records 1878-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Physical Education for Women (University of Michigan) records 1878-1972
University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education for Women.
9 linear feet
University of Michigan department responsible for administering and teaching required curriculum in physical education for women and overseeing recreational sports for women. Records include annual reports, minutes of staff meetings, scrapbooks, topical files, history of physical education for women at the University, and other materials relating to the Women's Athletic Association; also photographs
87147 Bimu C205 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Dept. of Physical Education for Women (donor no. 962 ) in several accessions beginning in 1939.
The records are open for research.
Classes in physical education for women were first conducted in 1894. Barbour gymnasium for women was completed in 1898, in expectation of which Eliza M. Mosher, M.D., was named professor of hygiene and was put in charge of the Women's Gymnasium. The Women's Athletic Association was organized in 1905, and in 1908/09 a women's athletic field (Palmer Field) was purchased and equipped. The regents established a Department of Physical Education and a Division of Hygiene and Public Health in 1929. The teacher training program in physical education became part of the School of Education when it became an independent unit in 1921. A master's program (1931) and a doctoral program (1940) were later added. Margaret Bell was appointed assistant professor of physical education, director of physical education for women and physician in the health service in 1923.
Photos of women involved in athletics and other physical activities, including dance, Lantern Night, and Freshman Week; also photos of Barbour Gymnasium, Women's Athletic Building, the Health Service, and the Michigan League.
Subjects:
Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physical education and training.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan. Women's Athletic Association.; Athletes--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women athletes--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education for Women.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Barbour Gymnasium (University of Michigan); Dancing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan League.; Recreation.; Sports.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education for Women.; University of Michigan. Freshman Week.; University of Michigan. University Health Service.; University of Michigan. Lantern Night.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan--Students.; Women.; Women's Athletic Building (University of Michigan); Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Card file index of women P.E. Majors 1924-1972 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks 1923-1968
  Scrapbooks contain clippings and programs detailing women's athletic and campus events, including extensive information on World War II era activities.
  - 1923-1936, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1937-March 1951, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - March 1951-1968, 3 volumes (Box 3)
- Annual reports
  The Annual Reports series consists of bound, highly detailed reports on men's and women's physical education with information on the curriculum, requirements, programs, enrollment, staff, services, budgets, teacher training, club activities, club sports and intramural tournaments and Women's Athletic Association summaries.
  - 1930/31-1941/42 (Box 4)
  - 1942/43-1953/54 (Box 5)
  - 1954/55-1966/67 (Box 6)
  - 1967/68-1969/70 (Box 7)
- Staff meeting minutes
  - 1946/47-1969/70 (Box 7)
- Histories and Miscellaneous
  - Printed materials (Box 7)
  - Conference on Curriculum Problems in Physical Education, summer session 1938 (Box 7)
  - History of Women's Athletic Association (Box 7)
  - History of Physical Education for Women (Box 7)
  - Curriculum in Physical Education (Box 7)
  - "Major" Day file (Box 7)
  - Card file of women's physical education majors 1924-1972 (Box 1)
- Topical files circa 1942-1972
  - Accidents to students (Box 8)
  - Alumnae Council (Box 8)
  - American Association for Health-Physical Education-Recreation
    - Student Section (Box 8)
    - Division of Girls and Women's Sports (Box 8)
    - Honor Awards (Box 8)
  - Bureau of School Services (Box 8)
  - Committees (Box 8)
  - Competition for Women (Box 8)
  - Dance Competition (Box 8)
  - Department Organization (Box 8)
  - Department of Physical Education and Athletics (Box 8)
  - Department Research Project (Box 8)
  - Facilities (Box 8)
  - Graduate Program in Physical Education (Box 8)
  - Graduate Students (Box 8)
  - Handbooks (Women) (Box 8)
  - LPGA Golf School (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Personnel (Box 8)
  - Physical Education Elective Program 1969 (Box 8)
  - Publicity (Box 8)
  - Recruitment
    - Recruitment Committee 1969-1970 (Box 8)
    - Open house 1968-1969 (Box 8)
    - Open house 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Recruitment Day 1967 (Box 8)
    - High School Career Day (Box 8)
    - Recruitment Day 1961 (Box 8)
    - Recruitment Committee 1959-1960 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Registrar's Office
    - Orientation program (Box 8)
    - Use of Gymnasium (Box 8)
    - Records Office (Box 8)
  - Safety Procedures (Box 8)
  - School of Education (Dean) (Box 8)
  - School of Education (Committees and General) (Box 8)
  - Speech Department (Box 8)
  - Staff, Lists, etc. (Box 8)
  - Steering Advisory Committee (Box 8)
  - Student-Community relations (Box 8)
  - Theses (Box 8)
  - U.S. Field Hockey Association (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists of prints and some negatives of women involved in athletics and other physical activities, including dance, often taking place in Barbour Gymnasium or at Palmer Field. The bulk of the photos are from the 1910-1935 period. There are also photographs of social events sponsored by the Department of Physical Education for Women and the Women's Athletic Association, including Lantern Night, and Freshman Week as well as photos of Barbour Gymnasium, Women's Athletic Building, the Health Service, and the Michigan League.
  - Card file of photo descriptions [incomplete] (Box 9)
  - Archery (Box 9)
  - Badminton (Box 9)
  - Barbour Gymnasium (Box 9)
  - Basketball (Box 9)
  - Bowling (Box 9)
  - Correctives (Box 9)
  - Crew (Box 9)
  - Dance (Box 9)
  - Dance, Clog and tap (Box 9)
  - Dance, Folk (Box 9)
  - Dance, Modern (Box 9)
  - Faculty (Box 9)
  - Fencing (Box 9)
  - Field hockey (Box 9)
  - Former presidents and house athletic managers (Box 9)
  - Freshman Week (Box 9)
  - Golf (Box 9)
    (na 9014)
  - Gymnastics (Box 9)
  - Health Service (Box 9)
  - Indoor sports and other activities (Box 9)
  - Lantern Night (Box 9)
  - Michigan League (Box 9)
  - Outdoor sports (Box 9)
  - Riding (Box 9)
  - Rifle (Box 9)
  - Soccer (Box 9)
  - Softball (Box 9)
  - Stunts (Box 9)
  - Swimming (Box 9)
  - Tennis (Box 9)
  - Track and field (Box 9)
  - Volleyball (Box 9)
  - Women's Athletic Building (Box 9)
  - Negatives (Box 9)
    (ca. 25 original 5x7 and 8x10 negatives of some of the photos listed above.)